<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Ethnography | Rozum S, UXR</title>
    <link>/tag/ethnography/</link>
      <atom:link href="/tag/ethnography/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Ethnography</description>
    <generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>2025</copyright><lastBuildDate>Mon, 08 Feb 2021 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>/images/icon_hu449a538eeebba9d4c918dd87510d1479_14176_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_2.png</url>
      <title>Ethnography</title>
      <link>/tag/ethnography/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Digital ethnography, or naming miracle</title>
      <link>/post/digital-ethnography/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Feb 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/digital-ethnography/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;about-project&#34;&gt;About project&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The product owner (PO) had an idea to make the new product for accountants. To get approval from high management, she had to provide the scope of accountants&#39; problems, which this new product could solve.
So she asked me to make several interviews with some accountants, to get this scope.  She didn&amp;rsquo;t have a team for this product, so I worked as a one-man team.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first and main objective was to understand typical accountant problems. But, there was a problem with time - we had only 1 week to provide the results. The second problem lied in the budget field - we didn&amp;rsquo;t have any money to recruit respondents.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;my-work&#34;&gt;My work&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Usually, you either don&amp;rsquo;t have time to recruit or don&amp;rsquo;t have money to hire a recruitment agency. Lack of both brings up the need for some creative solution. I found the solution by choosing a different way to get the needed information. The objective was just to get the initial information. In this case, you can get by without interviews.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Crawling some accountant&amp;rsquo;s forums and groups on Facebook, I parsed 400 posts, containing questions or issues. Then I tagged each post and found several dozens of problematic themes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I solved the problem, but there happened to be one more obstacle. PO needed to present it as a research result, and management had some mistrust in the desktop research. So we needed to present the research design from the best side.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And here come some naming trick. I wrote about how parsing posts count as a &amp;ldquo;digital-powered non-participant ethnographic observation&amp;rdquo;, or just Digital Ethnography.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;result&#34;&gt;Result&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The presentation was successful, high-management was glad. PO got approval, some ideas for the product, and resources to make a more thorough research. After that case, our research team adopted this approach.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;reflection&#34;&gt;Reflection&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the one hand, it was not a great case for serious research. On the other, I solved the time and money dilemma. The research brought the needed information and got accepted by high-management. The second option for this project was to make several expert interviews with accountants in our company. But it was riskier - I could screw up and waste all my time in search of respondents. So I still think it was the best way to get results fast.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
