<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Cases | Rozum S, UXR</title>
    <link>/post/</link>
      <atom:link href="/post/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Cases</description>
    <generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>2025</copyright><lastBuildDate>Wed, 10 Feb 2021 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>/images/icon_hu449a538eeebba9d4c918dd87510d1479_14176_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_2.png</url>
      <title>Cases</title>
      <link>/post/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Competitive usability test of three landing pages</title>
      <link>/post/landing-pages/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 10 Feb 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/landing-pages/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;about-project&#34;&gt;About project&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The company had several landings for the sale of services, its own and partners&#39;. Both types of landing pages contain the same services at the same prices. Even so, partner&amp;rsquo;s landing pages had two times more conversion rates than the company&amp;rsquo;s landings. And it was necessary to find the reason for this difference. As a lead ux-researcher, I was doing this project solo.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;my-work&#34;&gt;My work&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I had two major assumptions:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is a behavioral difference - people, who see compare several providers using third party partner&amp;rsquo;s pages, are more likely to make target action. They already saw all offers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s usability issues - it&amp;rsquo;s harder to make target action on company landing pages.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The second assumption was more effortless to test, so I&amp;rsquo;ve settled up with comparative unmoderated remote usability tests in several regions. 
I made six groups of respondents - two regions and three types of pages. The scenario was mostly identical, except for test data. The target action was to send a request for service. And the process of sending a request contains validation of the customer&amp;rsquo;s home address. For one region, I found the simple address ( i.e., Lenin Street, 25). For the second region, the test address was more complicated (i.e., Zhukov Boulevard, 36).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The process was quite normal - using Usability Factory software, I made several tasks for each group, sent them to respondents, got data, and started the analysis.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;result&#34;&gt;Result&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The difference in metrics was quite drastic. But it wasn&amp;rsquo;t the difference between partner&amp;rsquo;s and company&amp;rsquo;s landings. The company&amp;rsquo;s landing page got remarkably more SUM score difference between two types of test address than partner&amp;rsquo;s. And between SUM metrics, the effectiveness shows the most difference.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Further analysis showed that the main reason for this difference was the behavior of the address validation form. And the more complicated address, the more evident was the issue.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The form just didn&amp;rsquo;t let a customer use any abbreviations of the word except one right abbreviation. For example, the only correct abbreviation for &amp;ldquo;Boulevard&amp;rdquo; is &amp;ldquo;Bl-vd&amp;rdquo;. It&amp;rsquo;s quite an uncommon abbreviation.
&lt;img src=&#34;1.gif&#34; alt=&#34;Adress issues&#34; title=&#34;Address issues&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It wouldn&amp;rsquo;t be a critical issue, but weird behavior continues. The user doesn&amp;rsquo;t see a &amp;ldquo;Wrong address&amp;rdquo; type of error. The system shows the &amp;ldquo;You can&amp;rsquo;t get service at this address&amp;rdquo; error. 
So, it is not only easy to make a mistake. Also, you don&amp;rsquo;t know that there is a mistake.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But, this behavior is identical for both company&amp;rsquo;s and partners&#39; landing pages. It couldn&amp;rsquo;t be the causal factor of the difference in SUM. 
And now I want to talk not only about the mechanical behavior of the system. The main difference lies in one tiny detail, which shows the whole nature of the customer experience. 
&lt;img src=&#34;2.gif&#34; alt=&#34;Submit button&#34; title=&#34;Submit button&#34;&gt;
Partners&#39; landing pages allow a user to request a service even with an address, that was wrong from the system&amp;rsquo;s point of view. The company&amp;rsquo;s landing page shows the advertisement of the other service.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;reflection&#34;&gt;Reflection&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To let people send the form with the wrong address maybe just a lack of QA. And yes, it&amp;rsquo;s more logical and right to make the proper error message or make the more understanding address validator.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But even if this small thing is a mistake, it makes the form that is much more usable than the more technically proper form on the company&amp;rsquo;s landing page.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I love this case not only because it shows my skills in usability analytics. Also because it shows how much some minute trifles in usability could affect the whole product.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Digital ethnography, or naming miracle</title>
      <link>/post/digital-ethnography/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Feb 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/digital-ethnography/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;about-project&#34;&gt;About project&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The product owner (PO) had an idea to make the new product for accountants. To get approval from high management, she had to provide the scope of accountants&#39; problems, which this new product could solve.
So she asked me to make several interviews with some accountants, to get this scope.  She didn&amp;rsquo;t have a team for this product, so I worked as a one-man team.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first and main objective was to understand typical accountant problems. But, there was a problem with time - we had only 1 week to provide the results. The second problem lied in the budget field - we didn&amp;rsquo;t have any money to recruit respondents.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;my-work&#34;&gt;My work&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Usually, you either don&amp;rsquo;t have time to recruit or don&amp;rsquo;t have money to hire a recruitment agency. Lack of both brings up the need for some creative solution. I found the solution by choosing a different way to get the needed information. The objective was just to get the initial information. In this case, you can get by without interviews.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Crawling some accountant&amp;rsquo;s forums and groups on Facebook, I parsed 400 posts, containing questions or issues. Then I tagged each post and found several dozens of problematic themes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I solved the problem, but there happened to be one more obstacle. PO needed to present it as a research result, and management had some mistrust in the desktop research. So we needed to present the research design from the best side.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And here come some naming trick. I wrote about how parsing posts count as a &amp;ldquo;digital-powered non-participant ethnographic observation&amp;rdquo;, or just Digital Ethnography.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;result&#34;&gt;Result&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The presentation was successful, high-management was glad. PO got approval, some ideas for the product, and resources to make a more thorough research. After that case, our research team adopted this approach.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;reflection&#34;&gt;Reflection&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the one hand, it was not a great case for serious research. On the other, I solved the time and money dilemma. The research brought the needed information and got accepted by high-management. The second option for this project was to make several expert interviews with accountants in our company. But it was riskier - I could screw up and waste all my time in search of respondents. So I still think it was the best way to get results fast.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>To understand process right, draw process wrong</title>
      <link>/post/process-interview/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 06 Feb 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/process-interview/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;project&#34;&gt;Project&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the teams wanted to add new features in the internal assistant app for HR-specialists. But, at first, they needed to understand our hiring process from an HR point of view. They asked us to study the hiring process and find possible points of improvement.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;objective&#34;&gt;Objective&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our objective was to draw a process diagram for hiring activities in our company. And find some problematic sections there.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;my-work&#34;&gt;My work&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our team consisted of me and one other researcher. My responsibilities were to make a research design, write a scenario for interviews and pilot it. I chose in-depths problematic interviews as our main instrument. But, the pilot interview showed, that it&amp;rsquo;s hard for respondents to talk about the whole process. So we decided to draw a process scheme for respondents.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;result&#34;&gt;Result&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That was a huge success. Respondents started to speak more lively. Some of them even noticed errors and inaccuracies in our scheme and started to draw their variants. 
In-depth interviews gained some co-creative flavor, the physical scheme made the abstract interview easier for respondents. Also, the wrong parts of the scheme engaged respondents to give us more information about the process.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;reflection&#34;&gt;Reflection&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After this project, I used this trick several times. And it works every time. People need to correct other people&amp;rsquo;s mistakes works as a great ice-breaker. And visual stuff helps analyze the abstract process.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
