<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>in-depth interview | Rozum S, UXR</title>
    <link>/tag/in-depth-interview/</link>
      <atom:link href="/tag/in-depth-interview/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>in-depth interview</description>
    <generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>2025</copyright><lastBuildDate>Sat, 06 Feb 2021 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>/images/icon_hu449a538eeebba9d4c918dd87510d1479_14176_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_2.png</url>
      <title>in-depth interview</title>
      <link>/tag/in-depth-interview/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>To understand process right, draw process wrong</title>
      <link>/post/process-interview/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 06 Feb 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/process-interview/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;project&#34;&gt;Project&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the teams wanted to add new features in the internal assistant app for HR-specialists. But, at first, they needed to understand our hiring process from an HR point of view. They asked us to study the hiring process and find possible points of improvement.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;objective&#34;&gt;Objective&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our objective was to draw a process diagram for hiring activities in our company. And find some problematic sections there.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;my-work&#34;&gt;My work&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our team consisted of me and one other researcher. My responsibilities were to make a research design, write a scenario for interviews and pilot it. I chose in-depths problematic interviews as our main instrument. But, the pilot interview showed, that it&amp;rsquo;s hard for respondents to talk about the whole process. So we decided to draw a process scheme for respondents.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;result&#34;&gt;Result&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That was a huge success. Respondents started to speak more lively. Some of them even noticed errors and inaccuracies in our scheme and started to draw their variants. 
In-depth interviews gained some co-creative flavor, the physical scheme made the abstract interview easier for respondents. Also, the wrong parts of the scheme engaged respondents to give us more information about the process.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;reflection&#34;&gt;Reflection&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After this project, I used this trick several times. And it works every time. People need to correct other people&amp;rsquo;s mistakes works as a great ice-breaker. And visual stuff helps analyze the abstract process.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
